<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hagioi axioi, or, The saints worthinesse and the worlds worthlesnesse both opened and declared in a sermon preached at the funerall of that eminently religious and highly honoured Knight Sr. Nathaniel Barnardiston, Aug. 26, 1653 / by Samuel Faireclough ...</title>
            <author>Faireclough, Samuel, 1625?-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39584</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F107</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16705</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13033251</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13033251</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96802</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39584)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96802)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 738:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hagioi axioi, or, The saints worthinesse and the worlds worthlesnesse both opened and declared in a sermon preached at the funerall of that eminently religious and highly honoured Knight Sr. Nathaniel Barnardiston, Aug. 26, 1653 / by Samuel Faireclough ...</title>
                  <author>Faireclough, Samuel, 1625?-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 32 p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.D. for Tho. Newberry ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title partly transliterated from Greek.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Barnardiston, Nathaniel, --  Sir, 1588-1653.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Hebrews XI, 38 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96802:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96802:1"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, OR The Saints worthineſſe AND The worlds worthleſneſſe, Both opened and DECLARED IN A SERMON preached at the Funerall OF That Eminently Religious and highly honoured <hi>Knight S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</hi> NATHANIEL BARNARDISTON. <hi>Aug.</hi> 26. 1653.</p>
            <p>By SAMUEL FAIRECLOUGH, Paſtor of the congregation at KETTON.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 12.26.</bibl>
               <l>The righteous is more excellent then his neighbour:</l>
               <l>But the way of the wicked ſhall deceive him.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 <hi>John</hi> 5.19.</bibl>
               <l>Wee know wee are of God: But the whole</l>
               <l>World lieth in wickedneſſe.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Aug. Epiſt.</hi> 45. <hi>ad Arment.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laudandi ſunt atque praedicandi, qui non ſunt dignati etiam cum mundo floren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, florere.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. D.</hi> for <hi>Tho. Newberry</hi> at the Three Lions in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange.</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:96802:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Nathaniel Barnardiston</figDesc>
                  <p>Qui obiit a 4 Decemb. 1677 Aetatis 84.</p>
                  <byline>F. H. Van Houe. Sculp:</byline>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:96802:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:96802:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96802:3"/>
            <head>To the right worſhipfull and truly honoured Lady, the Lady <hi>JANE BARNARDISTON;</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">As alſo To the right worſhipfull S. <hi>Tho. Barnardiſton</hi> Knight, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Nathaniel Barnardiston,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Samuel Barnardiſton</hi> Merchants in <hi>London, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Pelatia Barnardiſton,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>William Barnardiſton</hi> Merchants in <hi>TURKEY,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Arthur Barnardiston</hi> Merchant in <hi>LONDON;</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Together with the moſt vertuous</hi> Ladies, <hi>the Lady</hi> Anne Barnardiſton, <hi>the Lady</hi> Anne Rolt, <hi>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>.</hi> Jane Brooke, <hi>M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>.</hi> Elizabeth Barnardiſton, <hi>and M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi>
               </hi> Thomaſin Barnardiſton.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F any one who is a ſtranger to your Family, ſhall (upon the ſight of theſe eleven Names ſubſcribed under your own) inquire as <hi>Eſau</hi> once did, when he beheld the very ſame number following his brother <hi>Gen. 33.</hi> and ſhall aske with him, who are theſe with thee?</p>
            <p>Your Ladyſhip may anſwer either as <hi>Jacob</hi> then did, Theſe are the children which God of his grace hath given me; they being all of them pledges of Gods grace unto you, as alſo heirs of the covenant of grace by you, and many of them approved veſſels of grace in themſelves, and patternes of grace to others: or you may uſe the words of that incomparable Lady <hi>Cornelia,</hi> when ſhee preſented her ſons to the Common-wealth, and anſwer with her, <hi>Haec ſunt mea Ornamenta,</hi> Theſe are my <hi>Jewels,</hi> theſe are my <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments;</hi> Gracious children being the Crown of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:96802:4"/>rents, whilſt like pure &amp; pleaſant ſtreams they ſhew the purity and excellency of that fountain front whence they did ariſe &amp; ſpring.</p>
            <p>But if your ſelf <hi>(Madam)</hi> ſhall inquire of me why I thus ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed them, my anſwer ſhall be this, That I was very ſenſible of that deep wound which the Lord hath at this time made in your ſorrowful and mournfull heart; and withall I was convinced what great care &amp; cautelouſneſs was to be uſed in applying com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts unto it, leaſt ungentle handling thereof, in ſtead of a cure, ſhould cauſe it to bleed afreſh. I alſo knew that cordialls can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be more tenderly and acceptably preſented to any parents bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heart, then when they are brought by the gentle and officious hand of their dearest children. And for this reaſon have I anne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed their names to yours in this dedication, that with one and the ſame caſt of your eye you may diſcerne the matter of your joy and ſorrow joyned both together.</p>
            <p>In this manner I obſerve the Lord himſelf comforting his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan Church, <hi>Pſal. 45.16.</hi> In ſtead of parents ſhall be thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, whom thou maieſt make princes in all the earth. Thus like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe doth the Lord Jeſus comfort his diſconſolate and ſorrowful Mother, <hi>Joh. 19.26.</hi> VVoman behold thy ſon, ſpeaking of the belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved diſciple. Yea ſo does the ſame ſon &amp; diſciple comfort his own heart, in all his ſufferings and afflictions, <hi>3 Joh. 4.</hi> I have no greater joy then this, to ſee my ſons walk in the truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> you have the ſame cauſe of joy, &amp; I doubt not but that if your Ladyſhip would ſeriouſly conſider of Gods love to you in this mercy of your poſterity, I doubt not but that as there is no joy ſo great, but the thought of one gracious child does much exceede it; ſo there is no ſorrow ſo bitter, but that the conſideration of ſo much pietie and obedience as your Ladyſhip may diſcerne in ſo many of your children, would abundantly &amp; ſenſibly ſweeten &amp; allay it.</p>
            <p>If you therefore, worthy Gentlemen, and vertuous Ladies, ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:96802:4"/>further demand to what end your names are thus inſerted, give me leave to anſwer you by relating to you what I have read in <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> that great Philoſopher, who tells us of <hi>Archilochus,</hi> who being deſirous to give ſome prevalent &amp; effectual counſel and advice to <hi>Lycambes,</hi> whoſe father was dead, did while he was writing his admonitions, by an elegant <hi>proſopopoeia</hi> bring in his Father, &amp; ſo put his pen into his Fathers hand, that <hi>Lycambes</hi> might receive thoſe inſtructions from one, who by his verie relation, was much more probable to prevaile, then himſelf. I have alſo met the like paſſage in <hi>Cicero,</hi> that prince of <hi>Oratory</hi> and eloquence, as the former was of Philoſophie; that he being to read a lecture of modeſtie and temperance to his friend <hi>Clodia,</hi> raiſed up her father <hi>Appius Cajus</hi> from his grave, and in his name delivered his directions to his daughter. Both of theſe in this practiſe of theirs intimating, that neither the wiſdome of the one, though the deepeſt Philoſopher, nor the eloquence of the other, though the choiceſt Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, is ſo effectual in the hearts of children, as the voice of a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, which is much more perſwaſive and powerful then any other argument or Rhetorick.</p>
            <p>Upon this conſideration it was that (being by all your earnest and conjoyned importunity overcome to give you a copie of that counſel &amp; admonition, which I delivered at your Fathers funeral) I have choſen firſt to preſent it to your deareſt Mothers hand, and thereby to reach and hand it unto you, that ſo it may be enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with authority &amp; efficacy; that as in times paſt you obeyed your Fathers inſtruction (according to the command of God <hi>Pro. 1.8.</hi>) ſo now for all times to come, you may fear to forſake your Mothers teaching, being thus conveyed unto you. Inſtructions that are onely ſpoken with the tongue are tranſient, and for the most part are terminated with the glaſſe: but directions that are written, are much more permanent, and many times, while thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb facs="tcp:96802:5"/>and take one Impreſsion, they alſo make and leave another. Laſt of all, as to my ſelf, this conjoyned dedication appeares not at all arbitrarie, but neceſsarie: for as the incitation to publiſh them, was from the ſollicitation of you all; ſo the end intended therein was the ſervice of you all, and the obligation neceſsitating my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thereunto was the united love of you all.</p>
            <p>For I must (and alwayes ſhall) acknowledge, that that God of my mercies, who granted me to find ſo great, &amp; ſo large a portion of love and favour in the heart of him whom the Lord ha's now taken into his own boſome, and alſo in the heart of you his deareſt Lady; hath likewiſe inclined the ſpirits of all you his children and poſterity, to manifeſt a ſingular and extraordinary affection unto me, which although I acknowledge my ſelf altogether unworthy to receive, and abſolutelie unable to requite, yet I hold my ſelf for ever obliged to embrace every opportunitie that is offered, to make my acknowledgement thereof unto each of you.</p>
            <p>And therefore have I greedily laid hold on this occaſion now offered to me, least if I ſhould have neglected this advantage, I might never have had the like again, by reaſon of my declining age.</p>
            <p>I cannot therefore but hereby give a publick teſtimony before the world of my ſerious apprehenſion, &amp; deep ſenſe of thoſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements, which both you, most honoured Ladie, &amp; alſo every one of you, renowned Gentlemen and Ladies, have laid upon me, and alſo declare my ſelf ſo firmly obliged to this whole Family, that I am extreamelie deſirous to the uttermoſt of my power al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to approve my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>your Ladyſhips and your poſterities</hi> Moſt devoted, faithfull ſervant in the Lord JESUS, <hi>SAMUEL FAIRECLOUGH.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96802:5"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Or The Saints worthineſſe And The worlds worthleſneſſe.</head>
            <head type="sub">A Funerall Sermon on Heb. 11.38. <hi>Of whom the world was not worthy.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>light of Nature</hi> teacheth every man this leſſon, that due praiſe, and publick acknowledgement of true worth in virtuous agents, is a great provocation and a ſtrong inducement, with all <hi>ingenuous</hi> ſpirits, to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate thoſe actions which are alwayes attended with <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> and <hi>admiration;</hi> according to that of the Oratour, <hi>Laudis ſtudio trahimur omnes;</hi> we are all <hi>forceably</hi> drawn by the deſire of praiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Morality</hi> proceedeth further, and tells us that an honourable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration of laudable actions, is not onely a <hi>motive</hi> and an <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement</hi> to the performance of the like by the attentive auditour but is alſo in great meaſure the very <hi>Guerdon</hi> and reward it ſelf, which is juſtly merited by the deſerving actour: for who knows not that <hi>Laus eſt virtutis praemium;</hi> honour is the reward of virtue?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Divinity,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God in Scripture aſcends higher, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96802:6"/>impoſeth it as a <hi>duty:</hi> leaving it not at our diſcretion, but making it a divine precept in ſacred Writ, to render to every man that <hi>praiſe</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> which belongs unto him, according to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Render to every man his due, honour to whom honour is due.</p>
            <p>All which being conſidered. I conclude that it is barbarous inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity in <hi>Nature</hi> injurious detraction in <hi>Morality,</hi> &amp; wilfull diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in <hi>Divinity,</hi> to bury the <hi>memory</hi> and <hi>reputation</hi> of thoſe in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and obſcurity, whom the Lord, by the manifeſtation of his <hi>grace</hi> in them, hath raiſed to eminencie, and exalted <hi>above</hi> the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard of the <hi>worlds</hi> worth and value.</p>
            <p>That I might not be guilty of any of theſe at this time, I have upon this ſad occaſion of the Lords removing out of the <hi>world</hi> a perſon of whom the <hi>world</hi> was not <hi>worthy</hi> (that <hi>Worthy</hi> of <hi>Worthies</hi> Sir <hi>Nathaniel Barnardiston</hi>) choſen theſe words, and made them the ſubject of my following diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Wherein you have held forth to you <hi>at the firſt view, the Saints worthineſſe,</hi> and the <hi>worlds worthleſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Both theſe are <hi>weighted,</hi> (as <hi>Beza</hi> notes upon the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) in a pair of <hi>Scales</hi> and <hi>Balances;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> de iis dicitur quae ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſa ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deris inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuntur, <hi>Beza</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18.</note> the ſtandard and beam, at which they are tried, is the wiſdome and valuation of <hi>the Lord himſelf,</hi> who layes a Believer <hi>naked,</hi> or clothed onely in a <hi>ſheeps-skin,</hi> and <hi>leathern coat</hi> verſe 37. in one ſcale; and puts the <hi>world</hi> with all its <hi>Glories</hi> in the other: and having moſt exactly pondered and tried the worth of both of them, concludes poſitively for the <hi>believer</hi> againſt the <hi>world;</hi> and openly declares that <hi>the worldis not worthy of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words for the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of them <hi>much</hi> reſemble that hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing on the wall againſt <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> Dan. 5.25. <hi>Mene menete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kel perez.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As if the Apoſtle had ſaid; <hi>Mene,</hi> O world all thy <hi>perfections</hi> and <hi>excellencies</hi> are numbred and finiſhed: <hi>Tekel,</hi> they are <hi>weighed</hi> in the <hi>balance</hi> with a naked <hi>believer,</hi> and found too light: <hi>Peres,</hi> and therefore the <hi>honour</hi> of all thy <hi>worth</hi> and <hi>excellency</hi> is taken from <hi>thee,</hi> and given to the <hi>believer, of whom the world is not worthy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the further interpretation of which words, although the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row compaſſe of <hi>one hour</hi> allotted to this duty, forbids <hi>me</hi> to meddle with any diſcourſe of the <hi>Analyſis, coherence, or dependance</hi> of the words, and <hi>you</hi> to expect any <hi>accurate diviſion,</hi> or <hi>prelix explication</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96802:6"/>of them; yet before I come to <hi>propound</hi> that <hi>one</hi> Obſervation out of them, on which I purpoſe to inſiſt, I ſhall borrow ſo much <hi>light</hi> from the <hi>precedent</hi> and <hi>ſubſequent</hi> words, and other Scriptures, as may open the text in theſe <hi>three</hi> particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What that <hi>world</hi> is that is ſo <hi>worthleſſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Who are <hi>thoſe</hi> perſons that are ſo <hi>worthy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. In what <hi>reſpects</hi> that <hi>world</hi> is ſo <hi>unworthy</hi> of theſe <hi>perſons.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. For the firſt, what <hi>world</hi> it is that is ſo <hi>worthleſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Text opened.</note> may clearly be underſtood by the <hi>oppoſition</hi> hinted in the text, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>perſons</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom it is <hi>weighed,</hi> which are believers; and therefore the <hi>world</hi> affirmed to be ſo <hi>worthleſſe,</hi> is the <hi>world</hi> of <hi>unbelievers.</hi> That <hi>world</hi> out of which the <hi>Church</hi> is <hi>called,</hi> John 15.18. <hi>That world</hi> for which <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth refuſe to <hi>pray,</hi> John 17.9. <hi>That world</hi> which cannot <hi>receive the Spirit,</hi> John 14.17. Together with the <hi>Trinity</hi> which that world worſhippeth, <hi>pleaſures, profits,</hi> and <hi>honours;</hi> as it is deſcribed, 1 John 2.16. This is that <hi>world</hi> which is here affirmed to be ſo <hi>worthleſſe</hi> and <hi>unworthy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>perſons</hi> affirmed to be ſo <hi>worthy,</hi> are manifeſtly deſcribed in the words <hi>before</hi> and <hi>after</hi> the text;</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. By their <hi>externall</hi> gath and condition.</item>
               <item>2. By their <hi>internall</hi> worth and diſpoſition.</item>
            </list>
            <p>For their <hi>externall</hi> garb and condition it is very <hi>low,</hi> and <hi>mean:</hi> for they are here brought forth <hi>in leathern coates, foodleſſe, monileſſe, eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, destitute, afflicted and tormented;</hi> yea <hi>harbourleſſe</hi> alſo, for they wander up and down and lodge in <hi>demes</hi> and <hi>caves.</hi> This and no better is the <hi>outward</hi> condition of theſe <hi>worthy</hi> perſons, expreſſed in the verſes before and after, 37.38. Their <hi>internall worth</hi> and <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> is ſet down verſe the 39. All theſe obtained <hi>good report</hi> for their <hi>faith.</hi> Famous for their precious faith, which is much more precious then gold, wherein they <hi>excelled,</hi> and were thereby <hi>dignified</hi> and <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured,</hi> both whileſt they <hi>lived,</hi> and alſo after their <hi>deaths.</hi> Theſe are the <hi>worthy perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. We will conſider in what reſpect the world is unworthy of theſe perſons. The world is unworthy of theſe perſons in a threefold reſpect, according to a threefold unworthineſſe mentioned in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Indignitas diſpoſitionis,</hi> an unworthineſs of <hi>diſpoſition,</hi> either by pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative undeſert or poſitive <hi>contempt</hi> as the Jews. Acts 13.46. are ſaid to be <hi>unworthy</hi> of eternall life, and the rich bleſſings of the Goſpel,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96802:7"/>for their <hi>deſpiſing and contempt of it.</hi> Thus though the believer, <hi>like the Goſpel,</hi> comes with <hi>fulneſſe</hi> of <hi>bleſsing,</hi> whereſoever he comes; being a bleſſing to the <hi>family</hi> where he dwells, as <hi>Joſeph to Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phars;</hi> to the <hi>buſineſſe</hi> wherein he is imployed, <hi>as Jacob to Labans;</hi> to the <hi>nation</hi> where he converſes, and to whom he relates, <hi>as Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham to all the nations in the earth;</hi> bleſſing them 1. with his <hi>prayer,</hi> as <hi>Abraham</hi> bleſſed <hi>Abimelech;</hi> 2. with his <hi>preſence,</hi> as <hi>Lot</hi> the city of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> 3. with his <hi>example,</hi> ſhining amongſt them to their converſion, as the woman, 1 Pet. 3.1, 2. yet theſe bleſſings the world <hi>contemnes and deſpiſeth, and perſecutes the bringers of them.</hi> And thus firſt the world is unworthy of the Saints.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Indignit as proportionis,</hi> there is an unworthineſſe of proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etneſſe and unſutableneſſe, as 1 Cor. .2. are ye <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to judge the ſmalleſt matters?</hi> that is, <hi>unfit, unable</hi> for ſuch a work: and 1 Cor. 11.29. <hi>yeeat and drink unworthily,</hi> that is, unfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, unſutably, otherwiſe then is agreeable to the pure fellowſhip with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in ſuch holy myſteries. So the <hi>world</hi> in <hi>this</hi> reſpect is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of the Saints, altogether unfit, unſutable &amp; indiſpoſed to live and enjoy <hi>ſociety</hi> and <hi>fellowſhip</hi> with them; <hi>light</hi> and <hi>darkneſſe</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no more oppoſite, then the <hi>Believer</hi> to the <hi>Infidel,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.14.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Indignit as pratii,</hi> there is an unworthineſſe of <hi>price</hi> and <hi>valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,</hi> as Rom. 8.18. I account not the ſufferings of this life <hi>worthy</hi> of the glory to be revealed, that is, not of <hi>equall</hi> and <hi>proportionable va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue,</hi> but of farre inferiour worth and virtue, ſo as they deſerved not to be named, not to be <hi>compared</hi> together, in reſpect of their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies. And in <hi>this</hi> reſpect the <hi>world</hi> is not worthy of the Saints, that is, it is of farre inferiour price, virtue, and excellency: the righteous even in ſuch a degree is more <hi>excellent</hi> then his neighbour.</p>
            <p>Which interpretation of the words ſhall be further verified in that obſervation, which as the reſult of the whole text, thus opened, I ſhall now propound.</p>
            <p>The Spirit of God ſetteth a farre higher <hi>price,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.</note> and <hi>valuation</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the meaneſt <hi>believer,</hi> then the whole <hi>world</hi> beſides; for of him the world is not worthy.</p>
            <p>The obſervation being ſo diametrically oppoſite to the judgement, practiſe, and that good conceit which the <hi>world</hi> hath of its own <hi>worth,</hi> and ſo perfectly contrary to carnall reaſon, and its apprehenſion, will ſeem but a meer fiction and chimera, at firſt hearſay &amp; be accounted a ſtrange paradox, impoſſible to be proved or maintained, (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96802:7"/>the Lord hath ſet his hand to the truth of it in the Text, and alſo hath given plentifull teſtimony to it in other Scriptures.) I will therefore in the further proſecution of it, 1. <hi>expound</hi> my meaning in it; and 2. <hi>demonstrate</hi> it, both from the <hi>testimony,</hi> and the <hi>practiſe</hi> of God himſelf whoſe truth it is.</p>
            <p>The meaning and ſenſe of the Point is this:<note place="margin">Expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> Take a man to whom God hath given but as much true <hi>ſaving faith, as a grain of muſtardſeed;</hi> and then ſtrip him naked, or clothe him but in a ſheep or goat-skin; turn him out of houſe and home, to lodge with wilde beaſts in dennes and in caves of the earth; deprive him of money, food, and eſtate; leave him under all the miſerie and torments that <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> and his <hi>inſtruments</hi> can afflict him withall: and then ſet by him <hi>an unbelieving worldling,</hi> clothed (with <hi>Dives</hi>) in purple, and all the bravery of the earth; put him in a palace as glorious as great <hi>Babek</hi> for his habitation; let his table be dayly furniſhed, for plenty of deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacies &amp; attendants, as the great king <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> his feaſt was, <hi>Heſter</hi> 1. put a <hi>world of ſuch</hi> men together, and I affirm that, what ever high conceit theſe men may have of themſelves, and their own felicities, and how contemptible ſoever the Saints condition, in compariſon of theirs, is reputed in this <hi>world;</hi> yet the Lord ſetteth a farre higher price and eſtimation of this <hi>believer</hi> at his <hi>worſt,</hi> then of <hi>all them</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether at their <hi>beſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this the Lord doth abundantly declare in Scripture, holding forth,<note place="margin">Conformed</note>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The verity of it.</item>
               <item>2. The equity of it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The verity is manifeſt,<note place="margin">As to the verity.</note>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. From the Lords expreſſions.</item>
               <item>2. From the Lords actions relating thereunto.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Lords expreſſions confirming the ſame are,</p>
            <p>Firſt thoſe terms of <hi>infamy,</hi> and appellations of <hi>contempt,</hi>
               <note n="1" place="margin">1. By di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions.</note> whereby in the Scripture he doth <hi>brand</hi> and <hi>vilifie</hi> the men of the world.</p>
            <p>Secondly thoſe <hi>titles of honour,</hi> and names of excellency where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he doth advance and <hi>magnifie</hi> the <hi>leaſt</hi> of thoſe <hi>little</hi> ones, that believe in him.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>unbelievers and men of the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vilifying the world.</note> the Lord <hi>brands them</hi> to their everlaſting contempt, with theſe and the like appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: as that they are the ſeed of the Serpent, ſlaves of Satan, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath, <hi>dogs, ſwine, vipers,</hi> yea <hi>davils;</hi> and all theſe for <hi>this</hi> purpoſe, to declare how <hi>unworthy</hi> and <hi>vile</hi> they are, in the acc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ount
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96802:8"/> &amp; eſtimation of God; namely, more vile then the baſeſt of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine which they tread upon: no creature in the world ſo contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as they are, except the <hi>devils,</hi> who are <hi>therefore</hi> worſe then unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, becauſe <hi>they</hi> made theſe <hi>ſo bad</hi> as they are; and upon the ſame account <hi>unbelievers</hi> are <hi>worſe</hi> then the vileſt of creatures, becauſe <hi>by their ſinne</hi> they have made the creatures ſo <hi>miſerable</hi> as they are.</p>
            <p>But on the other ſide we find in Scripture the Lord intituling the meaneſt believer with terms of the higheſt <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>reputation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Magnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Saints. Exod. 19.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Jer. 31.9. Rom. 8.27. Malach. 8.17.</note> as calling them his Jewels, his peculiar treaſure, his ſonnes, his firſt-born, his heirs annexed with his Sonne Chriſt; purpoſely to repreſent <hi>their dignity,</hi> and <hi>his eſtimation</hi> of them.</p>
            <p>Now let it be conſidered, that <hi>all</hi> theſe expreſſions and appellations, <hi>vilifying the unbeliever,</hi> and <hi>magnifying the Saints,</hi> were inſpired by the Lord himſelf, and penned by his Secretaries, enrolled in his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall word, publiſhed by his meſſengers; and all by his appointment, who as he is <hi>greater</hi> then the <hi>greateſt,</hi> &amp; <hi>wiſer</hi> then the <hi>wiſeſt,</hi> and <hi>bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> then the <hi>beſt,</hi> ſo he is too great, and too good, to <hi>deny,</hi> or <hi>unſay,</hi> what he hath ſpoken, or <hi>not to maintain</hi> the truth thereof againſt all gain-ſayers.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as the verity is thus manifeſt in the Lord his <hi>expreſsions,</hi> ſo alſo <hi>by his actions,</hi> wherein his high valuation of them is declared: in his actions relating unto</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Their redemption.<note n="2" place="margin">2 By divine actions. In redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. Pſal. 126.15.</note>
               </item>
               <item>2. Their remuneration.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, their redemption may be conſidered, firſt as temporall; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, as eternall.</p>
            <p>Firſt, their temporall redemption from temporall dangers. <hi>O how precious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints.</hi> God ſo values their perſons and liberties, that he will give all the materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all world, and the choiceſt of all the things and perſons therein, for the purchaſe of them, witneſſe the Prophet, Iſarah 43.4. <hi>Becauſe thou waſt precious in my ſight, and honourable, I gave Egypt for thy ranſome, and Ethiopia and Seba for thee:</hi> which are the places where the greateſt abundance of all the worlds riches, treaſures and pearls were to be found. And <hi>leſt</hi> we ſhould conceive, that the Lord did <hi>repent</hi> of the price he had given for them, and would do ſo no more, the Lord <hi>addes</hi> more in the next verſe, for ſaith the Lord, ſo do I value and priſe thee ſtill, that <hi>I will give man alſo for thee, yea people (and that in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eat number) for thy life:</hi> whereby it is moſt evident and plain
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96802:8"/>that the Lord eſteems one of his people at a higher price then all <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, Ethiopia and Seba,</hi> yea, then <hi>men</hi> or <hi>people;</hi> and as the late Comment gloſſeth upon that Text, God more eſteemeth of <hi>one</hi> of his <hi>faithfull</hi> then a <hi>whole world</hi> of <hi>wicked ones:</hi> which is the very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation that I am proving unto you.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the price and expenſe which the Lord was willing to lay out for their <hi>eternall redemption,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eternall.</note> doth more abundantly verifie this; for, ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 Pet. 1.19. <hi>Ye were not redeemed with ſilver or gold, but with the invaluable</hi> treaſure of the <hi>bloud</hi> of the <hi>Lord Jeſus.</hi> And the Lord doth not account them <hi>overbought,</hi> or <hi>dear</hi> at that rate; but profeſſeth himſelf well pleaſed, and abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>ſatisfied</hi> in the <hi>purchaſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 3.17.</note> yea the Lord Jeſus <hi>himſelf</hi> rejoyceth to give his bloud for them, Iſa. 53. whence it follows infallibly from <hi>the actions</hi> of God in their <hi>redemption,</hi> in laying out ſo <hi>great</hi> a price for their purchaſe, <hi>That one believer in Gods eſtimation is of more worth then all the world beſides.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the Lord declareth his <hi>high valuation</hi> of the <hi>worth</hi> of the meaneſt believer,<note place="margin">Actions of divine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> by the actions of his high and gracious <hi>remune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of their worth, declaring thereby that they are not <hi>onely</hi> more <hi>worthy</hi> then this <hi>world,</hi> but (in a Goſpel ſenſe) alſo <hi>worthy</hi> of the <hi>world to come:</hi> ſo ſaith our Saviour, Luke 20.35. <hi>They are accounted worthy of the world to come,</hi> and the <hi>reſurrection of the dead,</hi> yea, <hi>worthy</hi> of the <hi>kingdome of God,</hi> 2 Theſ. 1.5. yea, to be clothed with the moſt beautifull Robes of glory, Revel. 3.4. <hi>They ſhall walk with me, in white, for they are worthy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing therefore we have it under Gods hand in the Text, and in other Scriptures he hath atteſted it, both by his expreſſions in <hi>vilify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the world,</hi> and <hi>magnifying the believer above them;</hi> as alſo in the actions of <hi>redemption,</hi> and <hi>remuneration</hi> of them; it remains a moſt certain and undoubted verity, <hi>That the Spirit of God ſetteth a farre higher price and valuation upon the meaneſt believer, then the whole world beſides.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, as the Scriptures hold forth the <hi>verity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by the equity in reſpect of the world 1. Vilify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God.</note> ſo alſo do they declare <hi>the equity</hi> of God in this <hi>vilifying</hi> the world, and <hi>magnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the believer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The equity of the Lord in this <hi>vilifying the world</hi> appears thus; becauſe the world doth ſo much <hi>vilifie God,</hi> undervaluing him, not onely to the world, but preferring their <hi>ſins</hi> before him, yea, <hi>hating him</hi> (as the adulterer doth his wife for his harlot) in compatiſon of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96802:9"/>them, James 4.2. <hi>Ye adulterers and adultereſſes, know ye not that the love of the world is enmity to God?</hi> they deifie the world and vilifie God, whileſt on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> makes his <hi>belly</hi> his God, Phil. 3.19. another ſaith to the <hi>wedge of gold, thou art my confidence,</hi> Job 31.24. a third <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificeth to his own net,</hi> Habac. L. 16. and ſo deifieth <hi>himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is it not therefore <hi>equall</hi> that God ſhould undervalue the <hi>world,</hi> to the meaneſt of his <hi>Saints,</hi> that undervalue <hi>him</hi> to the worſt of their <hi>ſinnes? They that deſpiſe the Lord ſhall be deſpiſed,</hi> 1 Sam. 2.30.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Do not the unbelieving world account his Saints the <hi>filth</hi> and <hi>ſcumme</hi> of the <hi>world,</hi>
               <note n="2" place="margin">2 His peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note> and all things in it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13. rendring them the <hi>vilest</hi> people in the earth, as the Jews did <hi>Paul,</hi> Acts 22.22. ſaying, <hi>Away with them from the earth, it is not meet that ſuch fellows ſhould live?</hi> do they not thus vilifie them <hi>for the Lord's ſake,</hi> and the true worth that is in them? and therefore it is <hi>equall</hi> and <hi>just</hi> with God, to <hi>undervalue</hi> the whole world to the meaneſt of his <hi>Saints,</hi> for the <hi>evil</hi> that is in them that do thus <hi>vilifie</hi> his Saints for the <hi>good that</hi> is found in them? <hi>what meaſure they mete is meaſured to them again,</hi> Matth. 7.2.</p>
            <p>Again,<note place="margin">In reſpect of the Saints. Magnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God.</note> it is equall with God to <hi>magnifie the meaneſt believer</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the world, becauſe the meaneſt believer <hi>magnifies God,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferres the Lord above <hi>ten thouſand</hi> worlds; <hi>they eſteem all things in the world as droſſe and dung in compariſon of him:</hi> were it not for ſuch, God ſhould have but little glorie in the world be but little thought on, or eſteemed: theſe are they alone that extoll his name and glory above others, and therefore he eſteems all the world as droſſe and dung in compariſon <hi>of them,</hi> and values them above all others. <hi>They that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him ſhall be honoured,</hi> 1 Sam. 2.30.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,<note place="margin">Their reall worth.</note> the meaneſt Saint in the world is found to be of <hi>more true and reall worth,</hi> then all the world beſides. I would not be <hi>miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken</hi> in this, for I acknowledge that worth is <hi>a ſoveraigne attribute of God,</hi> and that <hi>primarily</hi> and <hi>abſolutely</hi> it belongeth to <hi>him;</hi> but yet, <hi>derivatively</hi> and in <hi>part</hi> it is attributed to the <hi>Saints,</hi> who as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaks, 2 Theſſ. 1.11. (when they are called of God to the ſaith) are (thereby) made <hi>worthy</hi> of that calling, by <hi>fulfilling them with all the good pleaſure of his goodneſſe, and the work of faith with power;</hi> as if he had ſaid, filled with all divine and humane worth, and all the worth of heaven and earth is communicated unto <hi>them,</hi> either by <hi>imputation,</hi> or <hi>infuſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96802:9"/>
            <p>Firſt, all the <hi>divine worth</hi> and <hi>merit</hi> of heaven,<note place="margin">Imputed. John. 1.16</note> I mean the <hi>merits</hi> and <hi>worth</hi> of our <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> is <hi>imputed</hi> to them: by which <hi>imputation</hi> they are ſo intereſted into it, that they receive it fully grace for grace.</p>
            <p>Secondly, all humane and ſpirituall worth is <hi>imparted</hi> to them,<note place="margin">Imparted.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing filled with the holy Ghoſt, Acts 4.31. <hi>Filled with all the fruits of righteouſneſſe to the praiſe and glory of God,</hi> Phil. 1.11. <hi>They are bleſſed with all ſpirituall bleſſings,</hi> Eph. 1.3. <hi>inriched in all things, in all knowledge, wiſdome, patience, humility,</hi> ſo that <hi>they are not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitute of any gift,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.5, 7.</p>
            <p>Theſe previous <hi>imparted</hi> graces make the believer (how mean ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever in other reſpects) much more <hi>worthy</hi> then all the <hi>world</hi> that wants them. Chriſt by deſcending into Jordan, raiſed it above the bounds of a <hi>corporall hath,</hi> to have the <hi>honour</hi> to become <hi>a ſpirituall laver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pliny</hi> ſaith that dedication of any thing to ſacred uſes,<note place="margin">Plin. Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. nat. hiſt.</note> 
               <hi>enhanſes</hi> the price of its and we all know that things <hi>conſecrated,</hi> as beaſts, or clothes, under the law, had <hi>greater</hi> worth and honour put upon them <hi>thereby,</hi> then either <hi>ſilver</hi> or <hi>gold</hi> had that wanted it.</p>
            <p>Every believer is a <hi>choſen veſſel,</hi> and <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſecrated</hi> to God; <hi>Paul</hi> being <hi>ſuch</hi> is better then all in the <hi>ſhip</hi> with him; and <hi>Noah</hi> better then all in the <hi>Ark,</hi> or in <hi>all</hi> the world beſides; in as great degree, as the <hi>richeſt diamond</hi> doth excell in dignity <hi>ten thouſand pebbles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Unbelievers are not worth one farthing in Gods eſteem, nay, they are worſe then <hi>nought,</hi> or a meer non-entity; for it had been <hi>good</hi> for them if they had not <hi>been born:</hi> take them at their beſt in all worldly excellencies and perfections, and <hi>if</hi> the Lord may ſet the price of all, he tells you they are <hi>digni damnatione,</hi> worth no more then damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Now then, ſeeing they are ſo vile, and the meaneſt believer ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, by reaſon of <hi>imputed</hi> and <hi>imparted</hi> worth into him; may not the Lord in <hi>equity</hi> and <hi>justice,</hi> preferre the meaneſt Saint before a world of them? there being a greater diſtance (in reſpect of worth and dignity) between the meaneſt and pooreſt believer in the world, and the <hi>worldling,</hi> (what confluence of <hi>parts, honours, and other enjoyments</hi> ſoever he enjoyeth) then there is between the moſt <hi>glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Saint in heaven,</hi> and <hi>the weakeſt believer on earth:</hi> becauſe the difference between the believer, is onely <hi>graduall;</hi> every believer in time will grow up to be ſuch; but the difference between the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96802:10"/>is <hi>eſſentiall,</hi> and ſo they differ in nature and kinde.</p>
            <p>All that now remains is the application and improvement of this truth upon out ſelves ſutable to our preſent occaſion; which that I may the better perform, I ſhall firſt apply it in relation to the perſon whoſe Funerall this day we deſire to ſolemnize, and then to the reſt of the auditory here met on this occaſion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>1</label> Firſt, I ſhall apply it in relation to that perſon of eminent worth deceaſed; which that I may do, I ſhall premiſe as an introduction three things by way of inference.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If it be ſo that the meaneſt Saint is of <hi>more worth</hi> then all the world, thence it follows neceſſarily, that the <hi>loſſe of one</hi> of them, is a <hi>greater loſſe,</hi> and more to be lamented, then the loſſe of <hi>a thouſand</hi> others, (how great ſoever they be in other reſpects.) If the <hi>daughters of Iſrael</hi> muſt <hi>weep</hi> for <hi>Saul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 24.16.</note> well may <hi>David ſay, wo is me for thee, my brother Jonathan;</hi> if there be cauſe to let fall a <hi>drop</hi> for the one, ſurely there is cauſe that <hi>our eyes ſhould guſh forth in a floud for the other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. If this be one evidence that the Lord values his Saints, namely, that he honours them, and remembers their <hi>faith</hi> and other <hi>graces</hi> (to their praiſe) many <hi>hundred yeares</hi> after they are <hi>dead,</hi> and aſleep in their graves; then ſurely it is a duty which we alſo owe to all Saints after they are dead, to ſpeak good of their <hi>names,</hi> and to <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peruate</hi> the <hi>memory</hi> of their <hi>worth</hi> and graces in the <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>eares</hi> of others that ſurvive them. The anointing of <hi>dead corps</hi> preſerves them from <hi>putrefaction:</hi> a good name is this <hi>precious ointment,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God hath <hi>anointed</hi> the corps <hi>before us above others,</hi> and doth therefore call us all forth, and <hi>warrant</hi> me eſpecially, to bring <hi>true</hi> and <hi>honourable</hi> teſtimony of his worth this day.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If God ſo values the meaneſt Saints, how much more did he eſteem this honourable perſon, whoſe <hi>graces</hi> made him (not onely more <hi>worthy</hi> then all unbelievers in the <hi>world,</hi> but alſo) more conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous and <hi>eminent</hi> then the greateſt number of <hi>true believers in the church?</hi> whereof if any doubt, or hath hitherto been ignorant, he will now certainly be convinced and aſſured, if he ſhall pleaſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member with me,
<list>
                  <item>1. His honourable birth.</item>
                  <item>2. His gracious life.</item>
                  <item>3. His bleſſed death.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>But before I enter the relation of either of them, I have a double petition to preſent to the Auditory.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96802:10"/>
            <p>And my firſt addreſſe is to his <hi>Right worſhipfull,</hi> mournfull,<note place="margin">A petition 1. To his Lady and her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</note> and lamenting <hi>Lady,</hi> with her <hi>children,</hi> who have called me to a work <hi>ſo difficult,</hi> and ſo farre above my power, as to delineate and repreſent the effigies and beauty of his life and converſation, <hi>which,</hi> indeed, <hi>was in heaven, whileſt he was here on earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This muſt be the work of ſome divine <hi>Apelles,</hi> and not <hi>mine;</hi> for how can the <hi>Sun</hi> be inlightned by <hi>a starre,</hi> or the <hi>fountain</hi> be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by its own <hi>ſtream?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore I humbly petition your worſhips to <hi>expect</hi> no ſuch thing from <hi>me,</hi> as that I ſhould give either <hi>your ſelves</hi> or <hi>the Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory</hi> ſatisfaction, in declaring either the greatneſſe <hi>of your loſſe,</hi> or the <hi>excellency</hi> of his deſert.</p>
            <p>Alas, you your ſelves neither <hi>do</hi> not <hi>can</hi> yet conceive or underſtand <hi>your own loſſe,</hi> much leſſe the <hi>want</hi> which the <hi>Church of God</hi> will find of him many yeares hereafter.</p>
            <p>And for the expreſſion of his deſervings, <hi>whence is it,</hi> that when <hi>your ſelves</hi> begin to remember and make mention of one or two of them, you preſently ſtop and forbear to proceed, and after a <hi>long</hi> pauſe in the midſt of your diſcourſes, looking one upon another, <hi>conclude</hi> with ſights and ſobs, and tears in all your eyes, but onely to ſignifie with theſe <hi>geſtures,</hi> what you cannot utter with your words?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Years,</hi> I confeſſe, are the beſt <hi>Oratours</hi> at <hi>Funeralls,</hi> and ſpeak much more effectually then any verball language can expreſſe; yet you ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving joyntly expreſſed what you can thereby, ſtill confeſſe all of you come ſhort in the proportion to his deſerts: how think you then that 'tis poſſible for <hi>me alone</hi> to ſatisfie both <hi>you</hi> and the <hi>whole Auditory alſo</hi> by my words; eſpecially conſidering that it is <hi>one</hi> property that belongs to things that deſerve <hi>admiration,</hi> that they cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed?</p>
            <p>All that I hope to effect herein, is to manifeſt by what I ſhall ſpeak, that <hi>I really intended his honour,</hi> though I <hi>actually</hi> perform <hi>no more</hi> then he that undertook to repreſent the beams and body of the <hi>Sun,</hi> onely by making a <hi>prick</hi> or <hi>dot</hi> of gold with his pen, in a fair ſheet of paper; or <hi>that Limner,</hi> who having undertaken to draw a moſt beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull picture, finding his skill <hi>inſufficient,</hi> caſt a vail over the face of it, to <hi>cover his own ignorance,</hi> as well as the beauty of the piece.</p>
            <p>My ſecond petition is to <hi>the reſt</hi> of the <hi>Auditours,</hi>
               <note n="2" place="margin">2. To the Auditory.</note> the ſumme whereof is, that they would not receive the <hi>teſtimony</hi> I ſhall deliver concerning him, as <hi>ariſing onely</hi> from the ſtrength of mine <hi>affection</hi> to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96802:11"/>his perſon, but rather from the conſcience of <hi>that duty,</hi> which I owe to the <hi>glory of God</hi> and the good of his peoples ſouls <hi>therein:</hi> for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I muſt ever <hi>acknowledge</hi> him to have been the Lords great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of good to <hi>me,</hi> and all mine, and therefore do <hi>deſire</hi> all of you that <hi>ever</hi> have received any <hi>benefit</hi> by my poor <hi>labours</hi> in this <hi>place,</hi> to joyn with the in thankfulneſſe to the <hi>Lord</hi> for him, (as the chief in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument thereof;) yet <hi>rather</hi> then I would ſpeak <hi>one ſyllable</hi> in this place which I did not either <hi>know</hi> to be true, on <hi>mine own</hi> knowledge, or believe it <hi>to be ſo</hi> from the teſtimony of <hi>unqueſtionable witneſſes of the ſame,</hi> I would have <hi>totally</hi> ſtopped my mouth, and impoſed an <hi>abſolute ſilence</hi> thereon.</p>
            <p>Onely let me further <hi>intreat you to conſider, that</hi> if the moſt of <hi>you,</hi> by ſome <hi>dayes</hi> or <hi>houres</hi> (occaſionall) injoyment of his preſence in his life time, <hi>diſcerned ſo much worth in him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Near 200 perſons met his corps al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt 20 miles from his houſe, and many thouſands attended his Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</note> that drew <hi>ſo great a company</hi> of the chiefeſt perſons in the countrey to go ſo long a journey <hi>before,</hi> and to come <hi>again</hi> ſo farre now to honour his dead corps to the <hi>grave:</hi> then you may eaſily gueſſe, that <hi>I,</hi> who had <hi>the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> to be ſo near him, and to be <hi>intimately</hi> acquainted with <hi>him,</hi> and his <hi>family</hi> for 30 <hi>yeares together,</hi> muſt needs have <hi>more perfect un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding</hi> and <hi>approved experience</hi> of his faith, <hi>holmeſſe,</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant gracious temper,</hi> then <hi>others</hi> could: and therefore what of a truth I know, and undoubtedly diſcerned in him, I dare not conceal; for <hi>veritatem celare, eſt aurum ſepelire,</hi> to conceal truth is to bury gold, yea, the <hi>gold of grace,</hi> which is much more precious then the <hi>gold of Ophir;</hi> which being <hi>truely</hi> (though <hi>ſparingly</hi>) diſcovered, will give us all cauſe to ſay of his <hi>life</hi> and <hi>death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. in vita con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</note> as is reported of <hi>Conſtantine, felix nativitas, felicior vita, feliciſſima mers,</hi> his birth was good, his life better, and his death moſt glorious of all.</p>
            <p>Now for the honour of his <hi>birth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to his birth.</note> I place it not in the the <hi>ancient lines of his pedegree,</hi> or the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of the Family, the continued deſcent of to <hi>many noble anceſtours.</hi> Although it be true that from his progenitours he was one of the <hi>Top-branches</hi> amongſt our <hi>Suffolk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedars:</hi> and although I acknowledge to be <hi>thus deſcended,</hi> and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter both then the <hi>commonalty,</hi> is a ſingular <hi>bleſſing</hi> of God to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons upon whom it is conferred, as <hi>appears</hi> by the Lords own words to <hi>David,</hi> in 2 Sam. 7.9. <hi>I have made thee a name like the name of the great men of the earth;</hi> yea, if they be gracious, <hi>great men</hi> are a <hi>great bleſsing</hi> to others alſo, as <hi>Solomon</hi>'s words import, Eccleſ. 10.17. <hi>Bleſſed art thou, O land, when thy prince is the ſome of nobles</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:96802:11"/>and not of an <hi>upſtart</hi> Family: Yet this is no other bleſſing but what is common to the <hi>worthleſſe world,</hi> as well as to the worthieſt believe, and ſo it can have no <hi>great excellencie</hi> in it; all noble bloud without grace being tainted: <hi>Gain</hi> was of the <hi>elder houſe,</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> of the younger.</p>
            <p>It is my purpoſe therefore to ſhew how the <hi>Lord</hi> honoured him in his birth, <hi>more then any unbeliever,</hi> which was by his <hi>ſecond birth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Genere no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitate no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilior.</note> whereby he received ſoul-nobilitie, and became <hi>heir to the ſecond Adam,</hi> whoſe hens <hi>are born not of bloud nor of the will of the fleſh, nor of the will of man, but of God,</hi> John 1.13. And this his <hi>ſecond birth</hi> was eminently honourable and remarkable above other <hi>in three par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. In the time of his converſion.</item>
               <item>2. In the matter of his humiliation.</item>
               <item>3. In the foundation of his faith.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. For the <hi>time of his converſion,</hi> it was when he was <hi>young;</hi>
               <note n="1" place="margin">1. The time of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion.</note> the Lord began to caſt in the ſeed of <hi>regeneration</hi> when he was at ſchool, the very time when <hi>others</hi> of his ranck and quality <hi>give up</hi> themſelves to the greateſt degrees of <hi>licentious wantonneſſe,</hi> and immoderare exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; pretending that the <hi>heat of nature,</hi> and ſtrength of the <hi>luſts of youth,</hi> are their diſcharges for the ſame: but at <hi>that very time</hi> did the Lord ſeaſe on him, who from that day, with <hi>Abel,</hi> did offer his <hi>firſt-fruits</hi> unto God. O how eminently and emphatically excellent it is for <hi>young Gentlemen</hi> to bear <hi>Christ's yoke</hi> in their youth, when the <hi>world</hi> haunts them, and <hi>nature</hi> prompts them, and <hi>Satan</hi> baits the fleſh and bloud of ſuch men with moſt deſireable things! O then to be <hi>crucified</hi> and <hi>mortified,</hi> is glorious, Lam. 3.27.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>matter of his humiliation</hi> was eminently remarkable;<note n="2" place="margin">2. Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> for whereas uſually <hi>in the converſion of young men,</hi> the Lord humbles them, by charging upon their conſciences <hi>ſome notorious actuall ſinne,</hi> it was otherwiſe with him; for <hi>living more innoceutly</hi> then (for the moſt part) young Gentlemen do, upon a time hearing that Text open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Pſal. 51.5. <hi>Behold I was born and conceived in ſinne, &amp;c.</hi> where the <hi>greatneſſe</hi> and <hi>odiouſneſſe</hi> of <hi>originall ſinne</hi> was preſſed; it pleaſed the Lord ſo deeply to affect his heart thereby, as that ever after it was a means to abaſe <hi>all high thoughts of himſelf through his whole life,</hi> and he was much more ſolidly and conſtantly broken for it, then for all the fruits of it, yea, hereby much preſerved from them: for as they that are once <hi>ſtung with ſcorpions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plin. nat. hiſt. <hi>1.7.</hi>
               </note> are ever after <hi>priviledged</hi> from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96802:12"/>
               <hi>ſtung with waſps and hornets;</hi> ſo he that is firſt deeply humbled for the root, <hi>mother and nurſe</hi> of corruptions, ſhall feldome have cauſe after to be wounded with <hi>the guilt of actuall tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. For <hi>the foundation of his faith,</hi>
               <note n="3" place="margin">3 Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his faith.</note> it was more remarkable then the reſt; for whereas moſt men <hi>ground their faith</hi> upon that which can onely be <hi>the proof of it,</hi> I mean the <hi>evidences of their love so God;</hi> and <hi>others</hi> (being better taught) <hi>upon the diſcovery of the all-ſufficiency of Chriſts merit, revealed in the Goſpel;</hi> and a <hi>third ſort,</hi> upon the generall offer tendering Chriſt unto them: his faith was not onely built <hi>generally</hi> upon the evidences <hi>of Gods love to him;</hi> but <hi>particularly</hi> upon the Goſpel, <hi>as it is the law of faith,</hi> held forth unto him in that Text, John 3.22. <hi>This is the command we have received from him, that we believe in the name of his Son;</hi> whence the preacher urging <hi>that in the Goſpel there was not onely granted a liberty to believe in Chriſt, if we pleaſed, but a neceſsity impoſed, that required us to believe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we will or no;</hi> it pleaſed the Lord ſo to overpower his heart with the authority of the precept, that he <hi>durst not refuſe it,</hi> but <hi>ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto it;</hi> and ſo his confidence was in pure obedience to God: which being the moſt evangelicall and ſublime reception of Chriſt, namely, upon no other ground, but the Lord his authoritative will, was <hi>that</hi> which produced this <hi>honourable ſecond birth in him,</hi> wherein his faith was more eſtabliſhed, then moſt believers uſually are all the dayes of their lives.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">In relation to his life.</note> that his <hi>life</hi> was <hi>as gracious</hi> as his <hi>birth</hi> was <hi>remarkable,</hi> you will certainly conclude, if <hi>you compare</hi> the moſt <hi>exact deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a gracious life,</hi> mentioned in the Scripture, <hi>with his practiſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his converſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether you define a gracious life in <hi>Davids</hi> words, Pſal. 119.1. <hi>Bleſſed are they that are undefiled in their way,</hi> &amp;c. or in the practiſe of <hi>Zacharias,</hi> Luc. 1.74. <hi>Serving God in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe all the dayes of our lives:</hi> or with <hi>Paul,</hi> Acts 24.16. <hi>living alwayes with a clear conſcience both toward God and man:</hi> you ſhall find his life a <hi>copie</hi> or <hi>counterpane</hi> of them all.</p>
            <p>As firſt,<note place="margin">In duties of piety.</note> for duties of piety to God, whether you inſtance in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret or publick exerciſes of Religion; he did ſo earneſtly <hi>devote himſelf unto them,</hi> that for my part (amongſt perſons of his quality) I think he hath left very few <hi>ſupersours</hi> therein behind him, <hi>if any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualls.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:96802:12"/>
            <p>I remember I have read it related, to the everlaſting praiſe of <hi>the Lord Harrington,</hi> ſo famous for piety, that it was his courſe to pray <hi>twiſe</hi> every day in ſecret, <hi>twiſe</hi> with ſome choice friends and ſervants, beſides his Family duties.</p>
            <p>But I am aſſured by thoſe that ſeriouſly obſerved <hi>this gracious Knight,</hi>
               <note n="1" place="margin">1 Private.</note> that it was his practiſe to humble his ſoul before the Lord in ſecret <hi>thriſe every day,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>oftener,</hi> if he could gain opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity; beſide Family duties, and other dayes of <hi>extraordinary hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation,</hi> which he greedily laid hold on when occaſion was offered.</p>
            <p>This I can teſtifie <hi>from mine own experience,</hi> that for many yeares together, when I was firſt acquainted with him, I ſeldome viſited him, or he me, but if any convenient place could be found, <hi>we might not part except we had prayed together.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor was he more frequent <hi>in ſecret prayer,</hi> then conſtant in <hi>ſecret reading the Scriptures;</hi> but never without prayer before and after, for the bleſſing of the Lord thereon: afterward he read <hi>other</hi> choice Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours, of which he had ſtore; but of late he took ſingular delight in reading M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Baxter</hi> his Treatiſe of the Saints everlaſting reſt, and <hi>preparation</hi> thereunto; which (ſince his death) I perceive was nothing elſe but the <hi>gracious event of divine providence,</hi> ſending it as a <hi>guide</hi> to bring him more <hi>ſpeedily</hi> and <hi>directly</hi> to the <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> of that reſt.</p>
            <p>For the ſanctification of the Sabbath ſo was it his delight, that for the moſt part, he aroſe <hi>the first in the family that day,</hi>
               <note n="2" place="margin">2 Publick.</note> and then would call his children and others up, that they might have time to prepare themſelves for a more <hi>reverent attendance</hi> upon the Lord in his <hi>publick ordinances;</hi> and for himſelf he ordinarily ſpent much time upon his own heart every Sabbath morning, <hi>before he came to the congregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for his <hi>eſtimation</hi> of, and conſtant <hi>attendance</hi> upon the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the word publickly diſpenſed, <hi>it was ſo eminent and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Miniſtry of the word.</note> that I verily believe, whoever in the congregation have been looſers by his death, <hi>we of the miniſlery have the greateſt loſſe:</hi> if the <hi>hearers</hi> put on <hi>blacks,</hi> the <hi>preachers</hi> have cauſe <hi>to mourn in ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth;</hi> for the godly miniſters had not a more <hi>faithfull and cordiall friend,</hi> and well-wiſher of his quality in the land: none ſo earneſtly and frequently prayed for them, none ſo highly prized their calling and labours as he did; he was fully of his mind, who openly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, <hi>he had rather fall with the Miniſtery of</hi> England, <hi>then ſtand in greateſt power with their enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When ſome talked of mortall bloudy times, and dark black dayes
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96802:13"/>coming upon us: he replied, <hi>that thoſe would be dark black dayes indeed, when the lights of the miniſtry were extinguiſhed,</hi> then the ſhorteſt life would be accounted the beſt. This made him ſo exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cautelous and ſerious, when any place belonging to his preſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was vacant, that he would ſpend many dayes in faſting and prayer to be directed therein: profeſſing many times ſolemnly unto me, that <hi>his ſpirit did more tremble to ſet his hand and ſeal to a Preſentation, then to any other writing or deed whatſoever;</hi> leſt (ſaid he) I ſhould thereby bring the loſſe of the peoples ſouls to be required of me or my poſterity, through my negligence therein. And therefore when <hi>by all his own care, and advice of friends,</hi> ſuch an one could not be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, that for his ſufficiency and abilities could give his own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſatisfaction, then he left it wholly to the better ſort of the people in that place, <hi>to chooſe their own Miniſter</hi> and Paſtour.</p>
            <p>In his <hi>perſonall attendance upon the word taught,</hi> what the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> requires in a bleſſed hearer, was his punctuall practice, for <hi>he was ſwift to hear;</hi> he could never ſatisfie his own conſcience, if he were not preſent to joyn with the congregation <hi>before there was one word ſpoken, or one petition ſent up to the Lord:</hi> his conſtancy in this courſe is <hi>notoriouſly</hi> known to you all.</p>
            <p>After the congregation was diſmiſſed, the firſt thing which he did uſually, after he came within his own doors, was <hi>immediately to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take himſelf to his cloſet, to begge a bleſſed dew from heaven, to water the ſeed ſown in his heart that day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>he that exceeded others</hi> in his diligence and reverence in other duties of piety,<note place="margin">Sacrament</note> 
               <hi>did exceed himſelf</hi> in his conſcientious preparation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and <hi>fruitfull improvement of the Lords Supper:</hi> for the moſt part he would ſpend a fortnight, never leſſe than a week before the Sacrament, in his cloſet, <hi>in reading, praying, and examination of his ſpirituall eſtate,</hi> with other duties of preparation tending thereunto; and what he <hi>practiſed himſelf</hi> in this kind, he conſtantly <hi>called upon others</hi> under him to do the like.</p>
            <p>Neither did this his ſingular piety <hi>in the things of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Duties to man.</note> make him (as it is in very many others) the more remiſſe or regardleſſe in the performance of the duties of equity, or charity, in his deportment <hi>to men;</hi> but on the other ſide rendred him much more <hi>exact</hi> and <hi>accurate</hi> in them all: for conſider him in his carriage towards others in <hi>their ſeverall relations to</hi> him, and you ſhall have cauſe to conclude his life as gracious in performing the duties of righteouſneſſe unto <hi>all his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:96802:13"/>as it was in the exerciſe of holineſſe, and the worſhip of God, and all acts of immediate communion <hi>with God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider him as <hi>pater-familias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Relative graces. Maſter of family.</note> the governour and maſter of a family, and it may be truely affirmed of him (whileſt he was a houſe-keeper) <hi>which the prophet</hi> David <hi>profeſſeth</hi> of himſelf, Pſal. 101.5, 6. <hi>That he walked in his integrity in the midst of his houſe: he permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to known profane perſon to ſtand before him, or wait upon him; but his eyes were ever fixed upon thoſe that were faithfull in the land, that they might ſerve him.</hi> He had at one time <hi>tenor more</hi> ſuch ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of that eminency for <hi>piety</hi> and <hi>ſincerity,</hi> that I never yet ſaw their like at one time, in any family in the nation; <hi>whoſe obedience</hi> joyned to their <hi>governours care,</hi> produced ſo rare an effect, that true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they made his houſe a <hi>ſpirituall church and temple,</hi> wherein were dayly offered up the ſpirituall ſacrifices of reading the Word, and prayer, <hi>morning and evening,</hi> of ſinging Pſalmes conſtantly after e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very meal, before any ſervant did riſe from the table: the chiefeſt of them did uſually, after every Sermon they heard, call the reſt into (<hi>that place of moſt diſorder in other houſes</hi>) the Buttery, and there repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Sermon unto them, before they were called to the repetition of it in their maſters preſence.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>relation of an husband,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Husband.</note> he ſeemed to me to imitate the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe <hi>of the Lord Jeſus to his church,</hi> in his conjugall love, protection, and full contentation and delight in her, untill he became a <hi>pattern</hi> and <hi>mirrour</hi> of matrimoniall <hi>faithfulneſſe and ſweetneſſe:</hi> and as it was ſaid by one of the <hi>Rabbins</hi> concerning <hi>Methuſalah's wife,</hi> that ſhe had <hi>nine husbands in one,</hi> for age and yeares; ſo I may ſay of his Lady, ſhe had nine husbands in him alone, <hi>for hus amtable carriage and graces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What manner of parent he was,</hi> let his children themſelves,<note place="margin">Father.</note> in their <hi>hearts, lives, and filiall deportments, declare;</hi> or do you receive the relation <hi>from me,</hi> as I have heard it <hi>from them:</hi> namely, that he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed not onely the part of <hi>an earthly father,</hi> in the manifeſtation of all <hi>paternall bowels,</hi> and <hi>tender affection</hi> to their <hi>bodies;</hi> but alſo executed the office of <hi>an heavenly father</hi> to their <hi>ſouls,</hi> by a <hi>continuall induſtry,</hi> and <hi>ſerious ſtudy</hi> for their education in the moſt exact and ſtrict way of <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>paternall</hi> Religion: witneſſe his dayly drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings in of moſt ſpirituall counſels, and gracious inſtructions; the grand ſcope and end whereof was, to ſtirre up and incite them to a ſtrict <hi>watchfulneſſe over themſelves,</hi> and a <hi>cloſe walking with God;</hi> and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96802:14"/>many times (after the giving of ſuch directions unto them ſeveralty) he would take them into his cloſet, and there pray <hi>over them,</hi> and <hi>for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If at any time they had offended him, <hi>ſo ſingular was his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and wiſdome</hi> toward them, that he would never reprove them, much leſſe correct them in his diſpleaſure, but ſtill waited the moſt convenient time, untill which time they ſeldome diſcerned that he was angry by any other effect <hi>but his ſilence. And on the other ſide,</hi> he was ſo ready to incourage them in any acts of wel-doing, that uſually all his extraordinary reſpects and ſavours to them, were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed <hi>rather as rewards of their duty, then the fruits of his bounty;</hi> ſtill profeſſing <hi>before them</hi> (as he hath many times of late <hi>to me,</hi> upon our conference concerning the <hi>extraordinary</hi> bleſſings of God upon them in their travells abroad and returns home again) <hi>that he took infinite more content in beholding one grain of grace, and evidence of true regeneration in his children, then if their eſtates and gains a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad had been multiplied an hundred fold,</hi> if withall they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned profane, or no more then merely civilized, without the power of godlineſſe.</p>
            <p>Again,<note place="margin">Pater pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria.</note> conſider him as a <hi>publick perſon,</hi> as he was <hi>pater patria,</hi> a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his countrey: which name he did deſerve, as well as <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Claudius,</hi> or the <hi>Decii:</hi> for although he did not in every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular what is ſaid of them, <hi>devoverunt, ſe pro toto terrarum orbe,</hi> they did devote themſelves for the defence of the whole earth; yet for his <hi>countrey,</hi> and the <hi>defence of the just liberties thereof,</hi> he did not <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe voluntarily</hi> to expoſe himſelf to <hi>a gulph of hazard</hi> and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: witneſſe his ſuffering under the impoſition of ſhip-money, coat and conduct-money, and the loan; for refuſing whereof <hi>he was long time impriſoned in the gate-houſe,</hi> and afterward confined for a long time in <hi>Lincoln-ſhire, above ſixſcore miles from the place of his own uſuall abode.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Witneſſe alſo his fidelity and integrity in the diſcharge of that greateſt truſt of all,<note place="margin">Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment man.</note> I mean his ſervice to his countrey <hi>as Knight of the ſhire, and member of the Parliament,</hi> unto which place he was conſtantly choſen on every occaſion; not that he had <hi>a patent for the place,</hi> as ſome of his enemies (in reſpect of his <hi>constant election thereunto</hi> &amp; out of envy at the peoples honouring him did caſt out; but out of the <hi>experience</hi> and <hi>confidence</hi> they had of his <hi>reſolution,</hi> and <hi>care to diſcharge the truſt that was committed unto him:</hi> whereby it came
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96802:14"/>to paſſe, that <hi>no ſooner was one to be choſen,</hi> who ſhould be intruſted with the power over the <hi>lives and eſtates</hi> of his countrey, but preſently <hi>the thoughts, eyes, &amp; reſolutions</hi> of all men, were fixed upon him, and all cried for a <hi>Barnardiſton,</hi> a <hi>Barnardiſton.</hi> Which truſt he received upon him, <hi>not out of any popular ambition,</hi> to advance his own greatneſſe; nor out of any ſelf-end, to raiſe his own eſtate by exhauſting the publick treaſury, or to inrich himſelf by other mens ruine; <hi>nor out of loftie arrogancie,</hi> that he might dominear and trample upon his neighbours in the countrey, under pretence of <hi>the priviledge of a Parliament man;</hi> much leſſe to abuſe that place to an impunity, and ſheltring of himſelf in <hi>riot, exceſſe, pride, and laſciviouſneſſe:</hi> but out of a mind and conſcience devoted to the ſervice of the <hi>church and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth</hi> therein; beyond which neither <hi>fear, favour, or flattery,</hi> could draw him to <hi>act,</hi> or <hi>vote</hi> at all, abſolutely refuſing to be defiled with <hi>the Kings portion, Abſaloms ſacrifices,</hi> or <hi>Achitophels policies or treacheries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As all theſe <hi>graces,</hi> and their <hi>exerciſes in his gracious life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Perſonall graces.</note> had their <hi>tabernacle in the Sun,</hi> were open and manifeſt in his courſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards others; ſo alſo his <hi>perſonall virtues and perfections,</hi> which, as ſo many rich <hi>jewells</hi> and <hi>mineralls</hi> in <hi>the earth,</hi> lay couched in his heart (as the <hi>cabinet</hi> of their <hi>habits</hi>) could not in reſpect of their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble actings, be <hi>ſo much hid,</hi> but that <hi>like the beams of the Sun from under a cloud,</hi> they brake forth and did ſhine out with <hi>ſo great ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour</hi> and <hi>luſtre,</hi> that the <hi>blindeſt</hi> eye could not but diſcover them: <hi>as to give you an account of one or two.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>graciouſneſſe of his ſpeech, ſo free from the leaſt unſavouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, beaſting or paſſion,</hi> that on the other ſide, nothing but <hi>love, ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>odeſty,</hi> as ſo many pure ſtreams, flowed from the pure fountain of his <hi>heart, still miniſtring grace to the hearers;</hi> ſo farre from the leaſt appearance of lightneſſe or exceſſive mirth, that <hi>in thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years together</hi> none ever heard one ſyllable tending to any wanton expreſſion, that might offend the chaſteſt mind or ear, to be breathed out of his mouth; but as the <hi>Poet</hi> affirmed, <hi>vernas eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at ab ore roſas,</hi> his tongue <hi>dropped honey,</hi> and his <hi>breath</hi> was as ſweet and ſavoury as in the ſpring.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Unto this I may adde the <hi>gravity and reverend awfulneſſe of his preſence,</hi> eſpecially in execution of Juſtice: of which I may ſay,<note place="margin">Greg. orat de laude Baſilii.</note> as it was of <hi>Baſils countenance,</hi> whileſt he was performing holy exerciſes, namely, that <hi>ſo much divine majeſty and luſtre appeared therein, that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96802:15"/>it made the Emperour</hi> Valens <hi>tremble to behold it.</hi> And in like manner his ſevere deportment was ſo effectuall, that it baniſhed from his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence all thoſe ſcurrilous and ſordid geſtures and practices, which the impudency of too many of his quality <hi>fear not to act in the ſight of God</hi> and their betters.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly, there was in him <hi>a bleſſed conjunction of thoſe things that rarely meet in any other,</hi> I mean both an <hi>admirable facility &amp; ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe to be intreated,</hi> with a great yieldingneſſe of ſpirit, even to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeriours, when any good might be done thereby; and yet alſo <hi>a ſtrong reſolute unmovableneſſe and ſtedfastneſſe of mind,</hi> in oppoſing all evil in whomſoever, ſuperiour or other, in the cauſe of the Lord: ſo that he was truely that which is <hi>reported</hi> of <hi>Athanaſius, Magnes &amp; Adamas;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen.</note> a <hi>loadſtone</hi> for his ſweetneſſe in drawing on good, an <hi>ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant</hi> for his courage and ſtoutneſſe in ſuppreſſing evil. In regard of the former, I may ſay as it is ſaid of <hi>Titus,</hi> he was <hi>delicia humani ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris,</hi> the delights of mankind; and in reſpect of the latter, he was <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaniel,</hi> a true Iſraelite without guile.</p>
            <p>The obſervation of theſe things in him, rendred him (not onely to me, but) to all that were intimately converſant with him (like <hi>Chemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi>) <hi>caput Veneris, &amp; gloria Christianorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Melchier Ad in zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra chem.</note> the beauty of grace, and the glory of Chriſtianity; which, <hi>as ſo many precious jewells,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned him, and preſented him gracious and honourable to all men <hi>whileſt he lived,</hi> and <hi>being dead,</hi> (<hi>as ſo many redolent flowers</hi> ſtuck upon his herſe) give ſuch a pleaſant and odoriſerous ſavour in the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrill of all ſpectatours, that the memory of them ſhall ever remain in the hearts and mouths of all future generations, who ſhall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thereby how the <hi>Lord</hi> was pleaſed to honour him, <hi>firſt with a ſpirituall birth, and after with a gracious life,</hi> and <hi>laſt of all with a moſt bleſſed death,</hi> which now in the next place falls under our conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</p>
            <p>And ſurely if their death be bleſſed <hi>that die in the Lord, and reſt from their labours, their works following them,</hi> Revel. 14. if it be a bleſſed death to <hi>depart in peace</hi> with <hi>Simeon,</hi> Luc. 2. <hi>our eyes behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſalvation by Chriſt:</hi> if it be a bleſſed death to die as <hi>Paul</hi> did, Phil. 4. <hi>having finiſhed our courſe, and kept the faith;</hi> or with Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, <hi>bleſsing our children in the arms of our dearest Joſeph:</hi> then the conſideration of the particulars following, which attended his death, will manifeſt to all that his death was as bleſſed as his life was graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, or his birth honourable.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:96802:15"/>
            <p>The firſt whereof was <hi>his carefull preparation thereunto,</hi>
               <note place="margin">His death bleſſed.</note> for the ſpace of two years before, when he made <hi>his laſt will and testament,</hi> and writ it with his own hand, upon this very ground (as he there expreſſes it) that after he had <hi>ſo ſet his houſe in order,</hi> he might have nothing in the world to <hi>look after,</hi> or <hi>look upon,</hi> but <hi>his bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> and <hi>Salvation by him.</hi> In which laſt Teſtament of his, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth ſo much <hi>aſſurance</hi> and <hi>confidence</hi> of the Lords everlaſting <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>love</hi> unto him, as if at the ſame time, with <hi>Simeon, he had imbraced the Lord Jeſus in his arms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the diſpoſall of the ſeverall portions to his poſterity, <hi>he doth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all annex and twiſt in</hi> ſo many heavenly counſels, and precious inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, tending to their everlaſting inheritance, <hi>that it rather reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled our Saviours Teſtament,</hi> conveighing the legacies of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace, or a heavenly Sermon, <hi>then any politicall inſtrument</hi> to diſpenſe onely earthly poſſeſſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A ſecond obſervable thing in his death</hi> was, his gracious welcome of the meſſenger of it. As ſoon as ever there appeared on his ſide a ſmall ſwelling, in which none but himſelf conceived any danger,<note place="margin">Gracious courage in ſickneſſe.</note> he taking me to walk with him, preſently fell into diſcourſe <hi>of the worth and immortality of the ſoul, of the manner of its ſubſistence and actings when it was ſeparated, of the joyes of the other world, and the vanity and emptineſſe of all things in this, as the things</hi> moſt ſutable to his preſent condition: and herewith he was ſo deeply and ſpiritually affected, that at our parting he expreſſed himſelf in this manner unto me;</p>
            <p>Sir, <hi>I now much wonder that any man that fully believes theſe things to be realities, and not mere notions</hi> (<hi>being in my condition</hi>) <hi>ſhould be unwilling to die: for my own part, I will not be ſo flattered with any carnall content, as to be deſirous to live longer in this world, where there is little hope left, that the Lord hath any more work or ſervice for me to do, except it be to ſuffer for keeping a good conſcience, in witneſſing against the apoſtaſies and impieties of the times: and therefore now it is a great favour of God to be ſent for ſpeedily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which paſſage I note, becauſe it was one of the laſt I had with him before his removall to <hi>London;</hi> and alſo becauſe I have certain intelligence, he made the ſame profeſſion to others, after he came un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Phyſicians hands.</p>
            <p>Where another thing is remarkable; for his pains and infirmities growing ſo faſt upon him, that he was thereby debarred the benefit of publick ordinances,</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:96802:16"/>
            <p>He one Sabbath morning obſerving the perſons in the Family were he lodged, preparing themſelves to joyn with the congregation of that place, <hi>fell into a great paſſion of ſorrow, and wept very ſore, and with</hi> David, <hi>poured out his very heart,</hi> becauſe he had gone with the multitude, and led them to the houſe of God, but now was neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to want the benefit of that which his ſoul ſo much thirſted for.</p>
            <p>Hereupon he gave himſelf ſo much the more earneſtly to the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of ſecret reading the Scripture, meditation and prayer, ſo long as his ſtrength would hold out: <hi>but one wave followed another ſo faſt,</hi> that he was diſable thereby to be ſo frequent and conſtant in thoſe ſecret duties of communion with the Lord, as he deſired: for which he made many complaints to his ſonnes, and others, as they came about him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The week before he died,</hi> he was perſwaded in reſpect of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of his pain, once or twiſe to go to bed before Family prayer: but the night following being again perſwaded to it, he told them he would not be intreated to do ſo any more: for he ſaid, <hi>he was ſure that he ſlept the worſe thoſe two nights for the want of it;</hi> ſpiritually uſing that proverb, <hi>whet it no let.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The day before his death,</hi> his children being about him, as <hi>Jacobs</hi> were, he bleſſed them all with his prayers for them, and gave theſe his laſt counſels unto them:</p>
            <p>Firſt, he admoniſhed them to <hi>take heed of worldlineſſe and vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory;</hi> ſhewing what a vaſt difference there was between a gracious humble man, and a proud graceleſſe man, both in the eſtimation of God and man.</p>
            <p>Secondly, perſwaded them <hi>to live in love and unity together,</hi> yet ſo as they ſhould ever count it their duty to watch over one another, and never be afraid to tell one another of their faults lovingly, and not to be <hi>mealy-mouthed,</hi> as his expreſſion was.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that they ſhould <hi>take heed of timorouſneſſe, and ſhirking from the truth,</hi> by reaſon of the oppofitions of the times againſt the Scripture-power of godlineſſe, ſhewing the danger of complying with man againſt God.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, he <hi>commended them unto the word of Gods grace, and the word of grace unto them,</hi> requiring them to be conſtant in reading the Scriptures, and to joyn prayer thereto for a bleſſing before and after.</p>
            <p>After theſe counſels, one of his ſonnes <hi>(telling him how much he
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96802:16"/>hoped the words of a dying parent would be regarded by them)</hi> deſired him to deal impartially with each of them, and diſcover unto them what evils he had noted each of them moſt prone unto, and what du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties he had obſerved any of them moſt negligent in. Which he did with ſo much plainneſſe, that <hi>one of his brothers</hi> ſtanding by, deſired him to uſe the ſame fidelity to him: which he did accordingly. <hi>A piece of affection rarely found expreſſed with wiſdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All that I ſhall therefore now adde further,<note place="margin">Peaceable and joyful departure.</note> is nothing elſe <hi>but the ſignification of that abundant raviſhing peace and joy that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted withall;</hi> wherewith his heart was ſo filled that he could not hide it, but declared it to all that inquired after it at ſeverall times.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to his ſecond ſonne, who obſerving him to grow faint, did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire him to chearfull: to whom he anſwered, Sonne, <hi>I thank the Lord I am ſo chearfull in my heart, that I could laugh whileſt my ſides ake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then to his brother then preſent, and inquiring how he found himſelf, he anſwered to the ſame effect, ſaying, <hi>O brother, bleſſed be God, I have abundance of raviſhing joy within me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame anſwer he gave to his eldeſt ſonne, who being called un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his father, and inquiring how it was with him, his father fell into an earneſt prayer, <hi>That the Lord would be pleaſed to give him a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py deliverance out of this world, and a glorious meeting with his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</hi> Which prayers of his the Lord ſo graciouſly anſwered, that as long as he had any uſe of ſpeech, he acknowledged the ſenſe of this inward joy; and after theſe words were uttered <hi>I have peace within, I have peace within,</hi> he ſpake no more, but lying for a while as it were in a ſlumber, at laſt he opened his eyes again, and <hi>lifting up his hands to heaven, fell a aſleep in the Lord.</hi> Whereby it is manifeſt that this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture out of this life was as comfortable, as his entrance into it was honourable, or his adode in it gracious and acceptable both to God and all his people.</p>
            <p>If any ſhall (as ſome of you may) object againſt this relation as partiall, ſaying, <hi>I have onely held out the flowers, but hid the weeds;</hi> declared all his graces, and concealed his vices; I ſhall return a <hi>three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold</hi> anſwer thereunto.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is not true to affirm that I have mentioned all his graces; for I have omitted divers, wherein he was as eminent as in any I have named. I might inſtance <hi>in his charity to the poor,</hi> wherein I have been altogether ſilent; becauſe the <hi>backs</hi> and <hi>bellies</hi> of ſo many, whom
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96802:17"/>he <hi>annually</hi> clothed, &amp; who for ſo long a time have been refreſhed by him, will proclaim it aloud to your <hi>eyes</hi> and <hi>ears.</hi> Yea, ſo farre was his heart drawn out in this kinde <hi>to the relief of the poor,</hi> that it hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended his hand by his <hi>last teſtament,</hi> as farre as <hi>the poor in new</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, unto whom he hath given a <hi>very conſiderable ſumme,</hi> for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of their miſeries and neceſſities.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If I had mentioned <hi>all his graces,</hi> and concealed his <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> yet my <hi>text,</hi> yea, &amp; alſo <hi>the whole chapter</hi> is both my <hi>pattern</hi> and <hi>warrant</hi> therein; for throughout the chapter, <hi>the faith and graces of the Saints</hi> are by the Spirit of God recorded to their praiſe, without mentioning <hi>any of their infirmities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, but <hi>in the third place,</hi> although I muſt acknowledge he was a man, and ſo <hi>weak</hi> and <hi>imperfect</hi> in every grace, yea a <hi>finfull man,</hi> and ſo <hi>ſubject to like paſſions and temptations</hi> that other men are: yet ſo free and pure was his life from any ſcandalous ſinne, or any other actuall evil courſe, that for thirty yeares together <hi>I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber nor he was ſoiled with any ſpot which might give occaſion to any to ſuſpect his eminent integrity and ſincerity,</hi> but his heart was yet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right before God; a thing very rare in the world.</p>
            <p>And now the application of the doctrine, in relation to the dead, being finiſhed, it remains that I next improve it upon the preſent Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory: and therein I ſhall direct my ſpeech
<list>
                  <item>1. To his Lady, children and poſterity.</item>
                  <item>2. To the reſt of the Gentry, and thoſe of chief quality preſent.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Uſes. To his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. Comfort.</note> to his right worſhipfull Lady and poſterity; his truth <hi>of the Lords valuation of the meaneſt Saint above the whole world, ſpeaks you a world of comfort in the depth of your preſent ſorrow;</hi> nay, it expells all ſorrow from your mourning hearts, and tears from your eyes; for how can ye grieve and mourn without hope for him <hi>whom the Lord values above the world?</hi> he who mourns with this hope, mourns with comfort, yea with more comfort then this world contains.</p>
            <p>I know where hearts have been knit together, they cannot be rent aſunder without pain. <hi>I find no fault with naturall affection;</hi> Chriſt wept for <hi>Lazarus, David</hi> for <hi>Jonathan:</hi> yet teas (as one ſaith wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily) ſhould drop like precious water out of a limbeck, not run like common water in a river: <hi>let nature have its courſe,</hi> when Religion hath ſet bounds to it.</p>
            <p>When news was brought to <hi>Xenophon</hi> (as he was offering ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice) of his ſonnes death,<note place="margin">Val. Max. lib. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>he put off his crown from his head and wept;</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:96802:17"/>but after he underſtood how valiantly he died, and worthy of ſuch a father, <hi>he put on his crown again, and finiſhed his begun ſacrifice.</hi> Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the firſt notice of your fathers death, you <hi>might put off your joy, and melt in tears;</hi> but now you have heard how graciouſly he lived, how bleſſedly he died, take comfort to your ſouls, and offer ſacrifices with joy and thankſgiving. <hi>Bona mors quae vitam non perimit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. Ser. <hi>35.</hi> de Diverſ.</note> 
               <hi>ſed adimit reſtituendam.</hi> The conſideration of the loſſe of friends cuts us, but our hope of receiving them again healeth us: the <hi>Egyptians mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> 70 <hi>dayes</hi> for <hi>Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Joſeph</hi> his ſon mourned but 7. Gen. 50.3. the reaſon, they mourned without hope, but <hi>Joſeph</hi> believed his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers preſent glory and future reſurrection, and this gave him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
            <p>The ſame glory he now enjoyes with <hi>Jacob,</hi> who whileſt he was alive, lived in near neighbourhood to God; <hi>his converſation was in heaven,</hi> and now his ſoul is there alſo, <hi>where it dwells in God, and God in it.</hi> Why ſhould you mourn for his joy, and <hi>wear blacks when he is clothed in white robes of glory?</hi> he is ſinging there, whileſt we are weeping here; <hi>he is triumphing whileſt we are ſighing.</hi> If you weep with thoſe that weep on earth, rejoyce alſo with him that rejoyces in heaven.</p>
            <p>I have alſo a word of exhortation from this truth to you of his neareſt relation;<note place="margin">Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> you have heard it proved that <hi>the Lord ſetteth a higher price upon the meanest believer then all the world beſides;</hi> you have the experience of it in the Lord his honouring your father in his life and death; and I believe you eſteem it none of your leaſt honours, that you are deſcended from alſo honourable a root, and that upon ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good ground, <hi>for to be heirs of ſo many promiſes and prayers,</hi> which he pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> up to the Lord for you, <hi>is an invaluable treaſure and por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes,</hi> when it was put to his choice, whether he would deny his <hi>Hebrew pedegree,</hi> and he reputed an <hi>Egyptian, even the ſon of Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh's daughter,</hi> and thereby have hopes of a kingdome, or on the other ſide, loſe all the riches of <hi>Egypt,</hi> by declaring himſelf <hi>of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity of Abraham:</hi> ſaw cauſe enough to make choice of the latter rather then the former: in like manner I am perſwaded you ſee more ground <hi>to glory</hi> that you are deſcended from your fathers loins <hi>(who was ſo gracious)</hi> then if you had been born <hi>heirs to the greateſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentate</hi> of the earth, if he were <hi>graceleſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O therefore that now it might be your great care to ſee that your
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96802:18"/>behaviour in the world may <hi>be worthy of ſo good a father.</hi> Beware you do not degenerate from his practiſe or principles; but le your converſation to God and mad be ſuch, <hi>that you may be a crown to his head,</hi> that was <hi>ſo great a glory</hi> to yours. <hi>Robora parentum referunt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beri:</hi> as ſickly children argue the parents weakneſſe; ſo a gracious po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity like pure ſtreams, demonſtrate the purity of the fountain from whence they are derived.</p>
            <p>Childrens grace and piety is not onely a <hi>comfort</hi> to parents whileſt they live, but alſo a <hi>glory</hi> unto them when they <hi>are dead:</hi> ſo was <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>akim,</hi> of whom you may reade, Iſa. 22.22. where the Spirit of God affirm <hi>that he was a throne of glory to his fathers houſe.</hi> I ſaw a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which one of you (ſince your fathers death) wrote from <hi>London</hi> to your brother in the countrey, wherein was this expreſſion, <hi>viz. that he ballancing his fathers gain and glory which now he injoyed in heaven, againſt the greatneſs of his own loſſe by his death on earth, he profeſſed, that if he might have him alive again with a wiſh, he durſt not deſire it.</hi> I liked the expreſſion exceeding well, becauſe it preferred his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers glory above his own content. And therefore as you rejoyce in the increaſe of your fathers glory in heaven, ſo labour the augmentation of it in earth, in being <hi>with Eliakim, a throne of glory to your fathers houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which you ſhall effect if (with the <hi>Rechabites</hi>) you ſhall ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and punctually obſerve and follow all <hi>his holy commands and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed examples,</hi> after his departure: in ſo doing both the Lord himſelf, and all his people ſhall do to you, as the Lord <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 22. promiſeth they ſhould do to <hi>Eliakim, viz.</hi> hang the glory of his fathers houſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abraham</hi> was a good father, and the Jews did much glory in him; but <hi>Abraham</hi> could not glory in the Jews as his children, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did no the works of Abraham their father.</hi> In like manner you had an honourable father, <hi>and you justly glory in him;</hi> O let him alſo have cauſe to glory in you, whileſt the world may take notice, that you both walk in the ſteps of his faith, and do alſo his works. Let me therefore exhort every one that hath any of his bloud in his veins, and beareth his name before the world, that you would <hi>become his repreſentatives the world;</hi> that he being dead in his own body, yet he may live and walk in you: Collect the <hi>jewells of his graces,</hi> ſet them in rows on the <hi>breaſt-plate</hi> of your heart, and ſo carry his image about the world in your lives, that all ſpectatours that knew your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96802:18"/>when they behold your conformity to him, may ſay, Surely <hi>this is that renowned Sir Nathaniel Barnardiſton,</hi> or one very like him.</p>
            <p>All this I ſpeak unto you in this day of the ſad obſequies of your father, that I may ingage you all, who are the <hi>branches of this noble vine,</hi> to become fruitfull boughs, loaden with ſuch cluſters, the fruit whereof may glad the heart of God and man.</p>
            <p>And for that end I commend unto you (next after the reading of the Bible) above all other books, the reading and remembrance of <hi>the hiſtory of your fathers life and graces;</hi> the volume of his counſels and directions written in your hearts: uſe all diligence in the daily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the ſolid principles, and divine rules, legible in his exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and practiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Boleſlaus</hi> the fourth King of <hi>Poland</hi> uſed to hang his fathers pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture in a plate of gold about his neck;<note place="margin">Cromerus lib. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> and when he was to ſpeak or act any thing or importance, did uſually pull it out, view, and kiſſe it, wiſhing he might <hi>do nothing unworthy of his name.</hi> The like do you in bearing his name for a remembrance before the world, untill the reflection on his perfections, (<hi>as ſo many rich diamond,</hi> caſting forth their beauty upon your actions) cauſe you to anſwer thoſe great expectations of piety and ſincerity, which your birth, education, and profeſſion, have raiſed in the hearts and minds of all ſpectatours.</p>
            <p>Conceive, I beſeech you, that every one that looks upon you, doth ſpeak unto you as the people of <hi>Rome</hi> uſed to ſpeak at the creation of their Conſuls, <hi>praesta nomen tuum,</hi> make good your name.</p>
            <p>By this courſe you ſhall in ſome meaſure make up the couatreys great loſſe in the death of your father, and make way for your friends <hi>to comfort thoſe ſorrowfull hearts</hi> that mourn for his death.<note place="margin">Ambroſ. in obit. Theo.</note> As <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> in his Funcrall oration for <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> thus cheared up his mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſubjects; <hi>my friends (ſaid he) let his comfort you in the death of</hi> Theodoſius <hi>the father, becauſe he lives in his ſon</hi> Honorias; ſo I may ſay, Let this comfort thee, O <hi>Suffolk</hi> in the loſſe of his worthy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triot, that his graces yet <hi>ſurvive in his ſonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, if you ſhall ſeverally and joincly ſecond <hi>your fathers piety in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity and zeal for the cauſe of God and your countrey,</hi> I may then adde that conſolation to your lamenting neighbours, which <hi>Euſebius</hi> reports of <hi>Conſtantines</hi> children, after their fathers departure; they lived ſo holily, that the people ſaid <hi>they had now may Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines for one before, they had Conſtantine</hi> multiplied: ſo we alſo hereby may ſay we have may <hi>Sir Nathaniels</hi> for one, or <hi>Sir Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaniel
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96802:19"/>multiplied</hi> and inlarged, whileſt his children that inherit his <hi>lands</hi> and <hi>eſtate,</hi> do alſo ſucceed him in his <hi>virtues</hi> and <hi>graces;</hi> who account it he <hi>highest honour of their family, that Religion be continued</hi> in a ſucceſſion and multiplication therein. And truely (Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen) if it was eſteemed the great honour of <hi>the Family of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rii in Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aeliax. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> that there aroſe out from that ſtock <hi>three excellent O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratours,</hi> one ſucceeding the other; what height of excellency muſt it needs be thought, that the power of Regligion and holineſſe is made ſucceſſive in your ſtock <hi>from generation to generation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The next application</hi> is to thoſe in the Auditory whom the Lord by his providence hath raiſed by their birth,<note n="2" place="margin">2 Uſe to Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> breeding and education, eſtate, parts, or offices above the reſt: <hi>Gentlemen (I mean)</hi> that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count themſelves, and are alſo accounted by others of <hi>an higher ranck and quality then other:</hi> whoſe preſence here is occaſioned by their reſpect and eſtimation <hi>of his noble Knight,</hi> now to be interred.</p>
            <p>To you I have a word of inſtruction from the doctrine already proved, <hi>which I am not willing to omit,</hi> becauſe I ſee <hi>the greateſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> that was born of woman, <hi>John the Baptiſt,</hi> when he perceived <hi>ſuch Auditours</hi> come unto him, which were not uſually before him, took then occaſion to apply himſelf unto them, Matth. 3. <hi>His practiſe ſhall be my warrant and incouragement</hi> to addreſſe my ſpeech unto you at this time.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen, I would inſtruct and direct you how you may <hi>be good as well as great,</hi> and become honourable before God hereafter, as you are before men already; and the onely way is this, to <hi>adde the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of grace to the nobility of nature:</hi> for ſeeing the meaneſt believer is of more reputation with God then all the world beſides, it doth follow, <hi>that the way to true honour is to become a true believer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By faith the elders obteined a good report:</hi> not onely a crown of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry after their death; but eſtimation and honour from God whileſt they lived, as is manifeſt the whole chapter before my Text. Faith makes the meaneſt believer of more worth than an Emperour. <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> a plain man, by faith became a Prince; yea, a Prince with God. <hi>Deo ſervire eſt regnare,</hi> to ſerve God is to be a King.</p>
            <p>You therefore that would be eſteemed worthy &amp; precious, muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come gracious. Oh <hi>how excellent &amp; precious doth godlineſs make thoſe men in the eyes of the Lord, whom birth and eſtate have made ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable</hi> in the eſtimation of men! Religion doth ennoble their ſpirits, and advance their mind unto the heavens: &amp; as a precious Jewell ſet in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96802:19"/>gold makes that much more conſpicucus which was beautifull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; <hi>ſo holineſſe addes to the ſplendour of birth and eſtate, the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emelings of grace and glorie.</hi> Be therefore humbly intreated to crowne the emmency of your bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th and fortunes, with the glory of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall excellencies.</p>
            <p>I am the more carneſt and ſerious at this time, becauſe the preſent pattern before you ſhewes it <hi>poſſible</hi> and ſeaſible for you: and, oh! that his death might cauſe you to imitate him, whoſe l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e was a light to guide you in the way. I know that many <hi>Gentlemen think</hi> that a <hi>ſtrict and holy life</hi> is onely for ſuch as have little to do, or to take to in the world. <hi>He onely is to live by faith that hath nothing elſe to live on:</hi> but for thoſe who are born to great things in the world, it is too low for them to <hi>ſtoop to Christs yoke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay ſome of them (who are <hi>not aſhamed</hi> of their oaths, blaſphemies, beaſtly uncleanneſs, ſwiniſh exceſſes, <hi>but glorie in them,</hi> yet) account ſanctification of Subbath, hearing the Word, conſtancie in prayer, <hi>to be their diſgrace;</hi> and eſteeme it a diſparagement to their credit to be accounted <hi>godly</hi> and <hi>religious:</hi> and therefore <hi>purpoſely</hi> act that which they know is <hi>profane</hi> and <hi>impious,</hi> leſt they ſhould be eſteemed <hi>holy or conſcientious. Thus Auguſtine</hi> in his Confeſſions <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. <hi>pudebat me non fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe impudentem,</hi> &amp;c. I was aſhamed of my modeſt, and bluſhed that I was not paſt bluſhing. And <hi>Salvian</hi> even with teares complaines of the Gentlemen of his time, Oh!<note place="margin">Deprov. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> ſaith he, ſuch contempt and diſgrace is put upon religion, <hi>ut cogantur eſſe mali, ne vide antur viles,</hi> they are compelled to be evil, leaſt they ſhould be eſteemed baſe for religions ſake. I wiſh that <hi>this ſin of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and ſcorn put upon religion, had been buried in Salvian's dayes:</hi> but are there not very many ſtill of theſe great ones, that think that their attendance upon the <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> in his Ordinances, is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion of their greatneſs, and abſtain from religious performances merely <hi>in point of honour,</hi> as too low a ſervice <hi>for their Lordſhips, Ladyſhips and VVorſhips?</hi> The <hi>CENTVRION</hi> thought his houſe too meane and unworthy to receive <hi>Chriſt</hi> into it; but theſe men think Chriſt houſe too meane and unworthy to receive them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doe any of the rulers believe? do the Knights, Eſquires and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men follow the Lord Jeſus?</hi> and why do they not? oh! it is not for their place, credit, reputation ſo to do. <hi>Oh! accurſed pride and helliſh loftineſs!</hi> is it the higheſt honour of the glorified Angels to be Chriſt his ſervants, and miniſtring ſpirits to attend his members? and is it the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96802:20"/>higheſt glory of the Trinitie to be accounted <hi>holy, gracious, pure, abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in goodneſs?</hi> and ſhall ſinfull duſt and aſhes, becauſe of a little precedency in birth, or eſtate, account holineſſe, purity, goodneſs, their diſhonour and diſparagement?</p>
            <p>It was the ſaying of <hi>Ignatius, antiquit as mea, nobilitas mea ſolus Chriſtus,</hi> Chriſt is my only nobilitie, and antiquitie: but theſe ſay, <hi>my nobility and antiquity is mine onely Chriſt:</hi> and therefor think the only way to caſt down themſelves, is to exalt Chriſt; whereas you may throughly be convinced by the truth proved unto you, that he only way to exalt your ſelves is to exalt Chriſt above your ſelves, who raiſeth the meaneſt of his ſaints to a greater worth then all the world beſides.</p>
            <p>You ſee, Gentlemen, that neither the Lord Jeſus, nor his ſervants do envie your honour, or greatneſs, much leſſe diſparage it; but rather deſire the advancement of it, in the true way of preferment to glory, <hi>without which it had been better for you</hi> to have been born and brought up in a cave, or den, and layn all your to have lived in your Palaces, and been ſed at your fulleſt tables: for</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Motives.</note> All your births and high eſtates (at the beſt) are no better things then the Lord beſtowes on his greateſt enemies, and if not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with grace and improved for God, they are <hi>greateſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</hi> For theſe expoſe you to more temptations then poorer men: as our Saviour Mat. 19. and the Apoſtle 1 Tim. 6. affirmeth, they are nothing elſe then fewel to feed your Juſts, and provocations to a more <hi>impudent</hi> and <hi>uncontrouleable</hi> courſe of ſins. Who would boaſt in ſuch a garment, which how rich and pompous ſoever it appears without, yet within fills the body with adayly brood of naſtie ſores, and crawling vermin? Such are moſt mens eſtates.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>higher</hi> your places are, the more <hi>notorious</hi> and <hi>conſpicuous</hi> are your vices. Gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mens offences are no more hid then <hi>the ſpots in the Moon,</hi> or a ſore in the <hi>face,</hi> which is a greater deformitie, then a wound or ſore in another part of the body. <hi>Nazianz. orat.</hi> 1 <hi>de fug.</hi> ſaith that <hi>nobilis improbitatis not am effugere non poteſt, niſi multum antecellit,</hi> a great man ſhall never avoid the brand of Impietie, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he much excell in ſanctitie. Oh how deformed then are they in the ſight of God, who improve their power to a vicious infecting of themſelves and thoſe that converſe with them!</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider that of our Saviour, Luc. 12.48. <hi>where God gives
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96802:20"/>much, bee lookes for much againe:</hi> the move your talents, the greater your account. Honour, birth, eſtate, are great bleſſings in themſelves. <hi>Great men may be farre greater inſtruments of ſervice for God and his Church then other,</hi> becauſe they have farre more power and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages by their places, to defend themſelves, and incourage others, in promoting the glory of Chriſt. As God made not flowers for toads and ſpiders for to draw poyſon out of them, but for bees to ſuck honey from them: ſo neither did he create honours and eſtates for his enemies, <hi>that being in honours they ſhould have no underſtanding,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 49.20.</note> 
               <hi>but live like beaſts that periſh;</hi> but for his ſervants, that will improve them for their Lords advantage.</p>
            <p>There is a day coming (Gentlemen) when the Lord will not only call you to an account for the <hi>principall</hi> of the talents of honour and greatneſs, but for the <hi>interest</hi> alſo. 'Twill not be your returning them <hi>in the napkin,</hi> by ſaying, you have not abuſed them, to the diſhonour of God and prejudice of thoſe under you; <hi>but you muſt return them multiplied and improved to the uttermoſt,</hi> in honouring the Lord with them: wherein if you faile, the more ſhame and contempt will fall on you, by how much you are truſted now with a greater meaſure of power and greatneſs above others. If all rationall men have branded <hi>Domitian,</hi> who (being a king) ſpent his time <hi>in cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching flies;</hi> oh! how much more will the Lord poure out confuſion upon thoſe who improve their places in ſpending whole yeares, and conſuming nights and days in <hi>compleating their luſt and methodizing their ſinfull wayes to an exactneſs: &amp; profunditie of voluptuouſneſs!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 9.7</note> theſe courſes render his Soul an <hi>Ethiopian</hi> &amp; Black-more, whoſe body is clothed in <hi>Joſephs</hi> parti-colcured coat, or the rich arras of Egypt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Conſider the only way to improve your greatneſs for you higher honour <hi>is to contemne it, yea looſe it, and deny it for the Lord and his ſervice.</hi> Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> improved the honour, title and dignitie to be ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, <hi>even by refuſing it:</hi> it was therefore that hee was raiſed to the title and dignitie to be called <hi>Pharaohs God, Gen,</hi> 7.1. Thus the 24. Elders Apocal. 4.10. <hi>improve their honours by falling down before him that ſits on the Throne, and casting their Crowns at his feet:</hi> thus our Lord Jeſus improved his honour in obedience to his Fathers pleaſure, namely, <hi>when he was in he form of God, &amp; knew it was to robbery to be equall with God, yet made himſelf of no reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and humbled himſelf to the death of the Croſſe;</hi> &amp; therefor God highly exalted him, &amp; gave him <hi>a name above every name, Phil.</hi> 2.8, 9.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96802:21"/>and if you ſhall be perſwaded to do ſo with your honours for Chriſt as he did with his honor for you, namely to deſpiſe it for is cauſe &amp; the cauſe of religion, and humble your ſelves, and take upon you the form and work of his ſervants, <hi>he will highly exalt you,</hi> and not only write upon you the <hi>name of the city of God,</hi> but the <hi>name of God himſelf;</hi> yea, he will write upon you his <hi>new name,</hi> and grant you to ſit with him in his Throne, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 3.12, 21. as he overcame, and ſate with his Father in his Throne. Which the Lord in his due time bring us all unto, by making the meaneſt as well as the greateſt of us, through faith, partakers of the merit and worthineſs of our Lord Jeſus, <hi>and ſo of higher eſtimation with God then all the world beſides.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:96802:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
